it might not be
clear what it actually means to practice
do something out of Faith as you know
you've been saying a few times recently
especially that just based on faith
somebody might
practice rightly it doesn't matter
whether they practice based on faith or
based on you know a ton of
um like reasoning but the point is that
they practice rightly but what is that
Faith yeah so whether you go you just
kind of described it there
in order to have faith
you need to know what you're actually
supposed to do that is directly related
to freedom from suffering
it's not other way around you're not
gonna understand what you need to do on
account of just Blind Faith yeah I'll
just do these random things and somehow
uh the way out of suffering will become
apparent to me no no so it's like you
need to understand to a degree what
needs to be done correctly
and then
uh
find the motivation to do it either
through reasoning or through faith let's
put it that way
because then it needs to be it needs to
be applied the effort needs to be made
so
so say somebody understands to a degree
gradual training what needs to be done
understands that the root of actions is
where your intentions are and all of
that and now he needs to start doing it
on a day-to-day basis and sometimes he
might not be quite clear as to why he
should always like not act out of
sensuality or why he should always be
watchful of intentions and why you
should do this or that that's within the
gradual training but out of Faith he'll
do it
he won't spend much time
but he hashing why should I do this what
I'm already doing he'll just stick to it
doing it but again on the right level
but you could see exactly because there
is
kind of less discernment
uh in regard to What specifically needs
to be done in terms of the correct right
training and practice it's very easy to
then start conflating that oh I'll just
emulate the external mode of behavior
and not question it and that's my faith
and that's well I guess you can call it
a faith but it's a completely not a
faith that can they can give rise to
satapat the other thing I was thinking about
the other thing I was thinking about
this is this you can
you can
sort of have a particular idea of okay
um like I have a lot of faith in such
and such
teacher it makes a lot of sense it you
know really makes sense to me I've
thought about it
um but now just kind of
um okay this particular contemplation I
was supposed to do let me just do it
that's something that you can do out of
just a sense of Duty or whatever but
it's not really possible to do the same
like to actually
um just not act out of unwholesome
things Be watchful of one's intentions
that's kind of not a particular thing
it's not a specific specific method that
you can just follow like that so that's
kind of I think the main difference that
it's uh or one difference
and the other thing is I think even just
in order to be able to do that you
already kind of have to be
um somewhat taking responsibility for
your own
idea or view of what you think or what
you believe should be done as in rather
than just oh so-and-so said or this is
this is what I believe in and let me and
also like sometimes if you hear
something that that does sort of
resonate with
with your current level of understanding
and so on and you feel inspired and you
feel like you have faith to do what that
person says well you should also ask
yourself and know like wait but what is
it that I find inspiring
like in hearing this teaching from so
and so I feel so inspired what is the
Inspire inspiring aspect
what facet of that inspires me uh am I
clear or
do I like or I don't know or oh well you
know as long as there is an inspiration
I won't question if I don't know you
have to because you might simply be
inspired by the way somebody speaks
and you still haven't understood what
he's saying yeah are you inspired by the
teacher who's teaching yeah but then
again like when you say okay I'm
inspired by the teaching okay but are
you are you understanding it correctly
or are you just reading into it what you
already think teaching is
and the the particular wording of this
teacher allows you to to put your take
on it it's like so you need to study it
you need to study it closer you need to
that's what we'll say it takes time you
need to kind of live with somebody I.E
you need to actually be exposed to what
they're saying for a period of time to
get to know them to get to see what they
say what they what they mean and so on
because again it's just words are just
shells in terms of like externally
approach they're just shells of the
meaning you don't necessarily know what
that person meant because those words
those shells might not mean the same to
you so all of that
so all of that
will already bring a discernment
authenticity and Clarity so then even if
even if you don't necessarily find a
specific inspiration through a specific
teacher by questioning like this well
you'll be able to inspire yourself
because you have the sutas you have the
stuff said and now you kind of know to
not just take it for granted because you
develop that habit of questioning it
so yeah then you won't need an external
inspiration in order to practice yeah
that was the other thing I wanted to
bring up like a faith often kind of the
idea of faith it does often imply faith
in a particular guide or teacher or
something or a method yeah something
palpable measurable that I can forget
myself about myself or my responsibility
and just do it just commit to it and do
it
which it doesn't not obviously correctly
at all I mean yeah you should follow the
method of uh watching your intentions
before every single action you make
throughout the day
so but
how much of a method that is well you'll
find out
but in a way yeah if you need a method
commit to a method of that of the right
kind but it's not it's not going to be
found on that level yeah
and that's and the reason that that's
called faith and that there is an
element of Faith always even if you have
all of the you know even if you're just
kind of committing absolutely to
you know reasoning and needing to
understand everything you still need to
have some Faith element because
where the work ends up really needing to
be done is on a level where you can't
supposed to give the example of the
other talk
recently about enduring things on the
right level
and you were talking about seeing them
as phenomena and so on and you
and you
there was one point then somebody made
this you know if you were to see it as a
phenomenon correctly that pressure won't
be felt but you don't see that end of
this when you're starting just
when you're starting just
having to kind of in learn how to endure
it on the right level and that's the
whole point like you can't kind of put
that results in front of yourself as a
kind of a carrot or something you need
to be able to
sort of just endure it without any
precondition or any
um
limits and that's like without seeing
the end of it without yeah that's the
that's the actual Faith that's where the
faith actually comes in
yeah so you know theoretically but once
you start doing it practically
you that theory won't apply your ideas
of it when you're pressured when you
have to endure they're not act out and
practice sense restraint
so again you can you can then mask that
by saying well it's my duty it's my
identity it's my it's the tradition it's
whatever or you cannot fall into that but then
or you cannot fall into that but then
yes then you won't have any other
confirmation or affirmation that what
you're doing is right and you just stick
to it to that extent that you don't know
and because again what you're doing is
simply refrain well what you're doing is
what you know you should be doing
which is refrain from centrality
not like that but obviously as I said
when those things are actively
pressuring you
you kind of
you need there is a there is this need
of okay give me some affirmation of this
somebody assurance that what I'm doing
is right although you know that what
you're doing is right you're not acting
out of sensuality that is already right
it might not feel how you want it to
feel but it is right so have faith in
that knowledge have faith in that
instruction and stick to it that's what
faith means so you realize really faith
in terms of like Sada from the sutas
should should be translated as
confidence not not faith I mean faith in the wrong
not not faith I mean faith in the wrong
once we clarify everything else around
it but more accurately it's really
confidence so I'm confident that what I
know I should be doing is the right
thing on account of reasoning on account
of everything else an account of
information an account of pondering so
I'm doing it out of that confidence
she's like I have confidence in
instruction implies that to that degree
you have some discernment of the
instruction like what are you confident
about but if you say our faith in instruction
but if you say our faith in instruction
means I just need to surrender to it and
my work's done like same I have faith in
Jesus or whatever
it's like no I have confidence in the
teaching okay well please explain the extent that
okay well please explain the extent that
you understood it that gives you
confidence then maybe I'll get the same
confidence but I have faith in it how well he's the
but I have faith in it how well he's the
greatest he's the best okay great so I
approve that's how I Faith because he's
the greatest his best I'll be the same
say I'll be saved I'll be the saved one
but like well that's not confidence that
is just a blind faith a reminder of The
Suitor I might read it no but it's like
even though you understand that that
pronunciation is peaceful yet
you don't do it when it comes to it
but when the pressure builds up
you give it up yeah even if I know that
it's peaceful I've reasoned it out to a
great extent why am I not what is my
mind launch out yeah towards
renunciation because develop confidence
in what you already know you don't have
enough faith in it or because you
haven't given them desire well no you
haven't given up desire because you
haven't given up desire and you haven't
given it up because you don't have
enough faith in giving it up
so the point is the time will come as I
said where no amount of your information
can do the work for you
and then you have to endure the pressure
of desire and that's where your faith in
what you know is measured
I I have no reason to not act out of
decentrality my mind is already made up
I'm gonna go I'm gonna take it I'm gonna
get it
but I know I shouldn't just that pretty
much remote abstract far removed no wait
whatsoever to it thought of I shouldn't
do it you have faith in that enough and
you won't do it
so yeah if you keep breaking the presets
means you don't have enough faith in not
breaking the presets
okay that Faith won't just magically
appear in these thoughts you need to so
if if you don't have enough Faith you
need to build it up you build it up
through developing that confidence
confidence that this is actually the way
are they this is what I fundamentally
want to achieve even through sensuality
it's actually achieved through sense
restraint peace equilibrium satisfaction
yeah so you're questioning what what
faith you have yeah you question what
you have see if you lack it and you like
it if you as I say if you keep acting
out and then uh actually start making
the effort so instead of just sitting
down and seeking chasing harmful
Pleasant experiences sit down and keep
re reviewing
revisiting and building up that
confidence in things that you know you
should be doing and yet you keep failing
you keep failing because you haven't
obviously thought it well through
because if you did it would have sunk in
deeper and that means when when things
are like the at the toughest point
you would have enough Faith despite of
how how pressure to act you are you will
have enough Faith to not act out and
just weather the storm
so you don't worry the stone when you
don't have faith in what you're doing
during that storm
I sense restraint
so how about how do I stop breaking the
precepts that's how you stop breaking
the precept by
constantly reflecting and pondering on
the dangers of doing so on the benefits
of not doing so on on everything else
that's involved like like your
day-to-day actions the the pedals of
desires the the
the disruption of peace all of that and
you will gradually be increasing that
faith and and being able to not act out
more and more
but it's not magically going to happen
on account of just practicing calming
then when pressure comes oh my mind is
disrupted now and everything that that I
heard before and that I know or even
that I understood has no weight now for
the duration of this pressure and I'll
just act out
that time has to come for everyone and
that's where you measure your actual
Faith that's we said that before that's
what like somebody like actual sotopana
because he might be lacking Faith within
you know within his great state of faith
and confidence on some specific aspects
he might not have enough Faith exactly
to stick to certain behaviors they would
be taking him away from sensuality
further so he would review that he could review
so he would review that he could review
that and I like faith in those crucial
little moments of giving in here and
there so what if I don't give in and
build up my faith through through
remembering truly collecting the danger
the battle the dissatisfaction
it goes every against everything that I
already worked for pretty much at that
point so Rico like that Ponder on that
frequently as the Buddha would say and
the mind will lean in that direction
but see people don't Ponder on things
frequently at all
with that kind of intent right intent
behind it like they might Ponder on
something and then adopt The View on
account of it and that's it my work's
done and then now give me a calming
technique a practice sensation watching
a bit of this bit of external Duty I
just do this because everybody else does
and I shall not be reflecting or
pondering or revisiting the stuff again
because that is unpleasant
but it's like no the practice is
frequently recollect again not
mechanically go through the words and
mantras but revise recollect bring up
ideas yeah exactly ideas contexts
information that you learned before
until the Mind actually starts to to
settle in there
and the more the more often you do that
the right type of recollection
the karma the mind would be the less
Disturbed and same when the Buddha says
in the suit is the
householder who has the right View
who has the right View
his samadhi he's Pleasant abiding like
Janna for monks is when he frequently
recollects the Buddha the dhamma the
Sangha The Unbroken virtue
again not as a blind recital to a golden
Shrine but actually recollects the value
the meaning the point his involvement
makes it alive through recollection and
diligent mental effort and there and
then he has Pleasant abiding there and
now nothing can touching
exactly exactly you can't have too much
of recollection
so if somebody lacks faith is because
they haven't recollected enough haven't
dwelt on it long enough haven't
clarified it long enough
and that's that is the measure actually
somebody can be full of Faith but has
zero confidence like if you were to ask
them if you were to interrogate them and
question about the practice they'll be
all over the place and there'll be
absolutely no confidence there
they still might be blinded by that
Faith they still might not accept what
you have to say yeah but their lack of
confidence in what in their own words
will become very apparent actually
that's nearly the more the more you lack
confidence the more faith you need you
to compensate it so you can't see the
discrepancy maybe you have real faith in
this teacher and but the the the
teaching is is discrepancy although
there are these contradictions which
you're not seeing yeah yeah nobody
doubts that that faith is real as such
but it's it's misguided
yeah exactly misplaced
so you know it's the sort to say like
the he has confidence in destruction then he
he has confidence in destruction then he
applies himself becomes a sortapana and
so he has faith in the instruction he
comes a sodapana and then he develops
confirmed confidence in the teaching in
other words he saw it for himself now
his confidence has been confirmed
there's a I was gonna say that's then
that confirmed Faith like the real
exactly so you could say he has
confidence to agree but he hasn't
confirmed it still thoroughly for
himself and for sotopana he has
confirmed confidence in the teaching
that is right because he actually is
free from suffering so there is no
greater verification of the truthfulness
and the right right practice there
um
so you could say his faith that then
gets confirmed but see when you when you
know now that this works you don't there
is no belief involved anymore now you
know you have confirmed it that it works
so you don't need to believe it and hope
that it works it works
of the hand having to sit on its eggs
for chicken to lay out to come out
safely you could say first time say
first time hand doesn't necessarily know
that if she lays on the eggs the chicks
would come out safely
he has
some confidence and some faith that
that's how it works
and then he does he does the work it
sits on the eggs and the chicks come out
safely then for the next time she won't
have to question it again because she
has confirmed that that's what it works
so in the beginning for the first time
she might have
doubt had a lot of Doubt of oh should I
get up now should I stay how long should
I stay should I leave how quickly I have
to return maybe this won't work maybe I
need to leave them alone for them to
hatch maybe all of these thoughts would
have been passing through its head but
if it actually sat on its eggs
the hands with the chicks would have
come out safely and then all their doubt
was just wiped away because it was
confirmed that that's how it works so
next time she won't have the same doubts
again because all she needs to do is
just not give in to those doubts because
she knows that what she's doing is
already right
she doesn't really any circumstance for
her confidence her confidence is is
independent of any at that point
afterwards yes exactly exactly exactly
yeah nothing can come in between that
that's exactly what it was described in
the suitors by that sortapuna who said
well even with the whole ball says one
thing and the Buddha said the other the
opposite like the Buddha is right not because
like the Buddha is right not because
he's a fundamentalist blinded lunatic no
it's because he actually confirmed that
thing for himself
so nobody can come in between that if
people say the opposite is because they
haven't seen it for themselves
so it's a direct directly visible Here
and Now
and that and that is and that should be
the criteria by the way even for
somebody before they become a sortabana
and and start practicing and so on like
the goals the results should be visible
Here and Now
you know okay initially it won't happen
overnight it's not an instant thing you
have to sit on the eggs
but okay but you know I've been doing it
for 20 years now like isn't that a bit
long
what is the Right View I've been
following this teaching or that teaching
for how long two days okay maybe for a
little bit longer two years okay you
know is there any anything to show for
five years ten years okay come on now
but not like just just dismiss that part
of
um results and still just
convince yourself that you're doing it
right no it it should be happening
so yes there is a such thing to be a bit
impatient but then there is a such thing
to like completely disregard the fact
that you will not know
you will not know
whether you're doing it rightly until
you confirmed it that it is the right
thing to do in other words until you
know for yourself until you're a
satapana
it comes down to not really disregard
not disregarding no disregarding the
goal your own age exactly what is my aim
when I have an A and you do what it
takes to get to now that aim obviously
as I said as you discern more
will will
become more refined let's say let's put
it that way then what it used to be but
fundamentally you need to keep it
in the play you need to keep it there is
a relevant thing because you are doing
this to be free from suffering so
are you free from suffering do you know
the way out of suffering for yourself
independent of any circumstances exactly
can something come in between it can
something cause doubt they would
completely change the course of your
effort or do you know for yourself Beyond doubt
or do you know for yourself Beyond doubt
cannot be shaken you know exactly
what suffering is and what escape from
it is exactly there's nothing that can
come in between it's like the most
direct thing you see and feel obviously
by that point
and you can kind of apply that
way of thinking even if you don't
know for yourself you can think
well is my current understanding along
the lines that could not be
turned upside down by something or
whatever exactly and and then we'll kind
of find out you can't go into like
particulars and turn them around to fit
without changing the whole thing yeah
exactly but kind of to to well to find
where you're understanding or
misunderstanding does not have that
nature of being unable to be well yeah
it needs to be needs to be sound needs
to be free from contradiction
free from uh like you might be
emotionally invested in it and which is
why it will be unpleasant to question it
and you're emotionally invested because
you know freedom from suffering is taken
personally it's important so that's fine
that's understandable but that should
not prevent you from questioning it
so you need to know
that it is a sound thing that can hold
the water as it said and uh so and it
exactly cannot be upturned by by the
opposing view in other words you would
see opposing view where the lag and
where it lacks but it doesn't add up
because you thought your view through
you didn't just accept it took it on and
now you know a disagreement comes or or
something that says oh well no that's
wrong and you you just you're just going
to defense mode without recognizing
weight but do I see where this Supply
maybe it's right
but if it is right do I know that it
isn't right do I know that I'm right
or do I just desperately need to believe
that I'm right and have to shut
everything else out
even if you're not
if you don't know for yourself
yet you can certainly not find fault
you can certainly not find fault
or any contradiction in the value of
sense restraint and say no to sensuality
you'll find a lot of pain in it
but that's not to say that it's not a
logically sound conclusion that it's
better to be withdrawn from desires and
attacked out of them and not scratching
the edge
you know that colloquial you already
know that everybody knows that it's just
they don't have enough reasons
because they haven't recollected
sufficiently enough
of the dangers the context the benefits
so they're like Faith they like faith in
sticking to it
this is that Suitor um
um
it says uh this is a Layman speaking to
uh Venable and under it says
enjoy essential Pleasures take Delight
in central pleasures and rejoice in
essential pleasures
pronunciation seems like a precipice to
us I have heard that in this dumb and
discipline they are very young
because who you know go forth and
Delight in that enunciation
but how come my mind doesn't Delight in
it even though I know in theory all this
the teaching already
so anyways
there's a bit of a further discussion
but the Buddha says before my Enlightenment
the Buddha says before my Enlightenment
while I was just a bodhisatta
it occurred to me good is renunciation
good is Solitude yet my mind did not
launch out upon renunciation and become
calm settled and liberated
in it though I saw it as peaceful
it occurred to me why is it that my mind
does not launch out upon pronunciation
then it occurred to me I have not seen
the danger in central pleasures and I
have not cultivated that Insight so
that's even before he was enlightened
yeah I have not thought about it
I have not achieved the benefit in
renunciation and have not pursued it
therefore my mind does not launch out
upon renunciation
and then
and it's then uh lady says if having
seen the danger in central pleasure I
would cultivate that insight
and if having achieved the benefit in
renunciation I would pursue it
since it is peaceful sometime later
having seen a danger in central
Pleasures I cultivated that Insight yeah
recollect it reflect on it
you get a degree of understanding then
cultivated understanding further so
that's your meditation that's your
practice not like mindlessly sitting and
not like mindlessly sitting and
switching the thoughts off and
experiencing Pleasant bodily Sensations
and then waking up from it and then not
knowing how to deal with stuff when it
starts pressuring you because you
haven't dealt with anything you just
shutting yourself down because you don't
want to deal with stuff that's pretty
much it and that's completely the
opposite of what the practice is
so reflect recollect sit down to
meditate quote unquote and by that I
mean sit down and spend an hour
dedicated out of your time
in like a motionless state of
recollecting and and reflecting and
cultivating the insights of the danger
the Peril and when you get off your
cushion the danger the traps the baits
will be all around you and you will not
go towards them and you will maintain
the context of the of the
dissatisfaction and and the precipice if
you do and all of that and learn how to
live among the bait without touching the
bait like the the deer hurts you need to
learn that it's not magically going to
be revealed and highlighted little
markers around the bait no you need to
discern that and maintain that and then
you become comfortable within it and
then obviously
uh having not been trapped for a long
time you're going to develop even more
confidence in it because you're actually
free you can run in between the bait
you can run in between the bait
and you will not get caught that's how
confident you'll be
you want it to shelter yourself in that
sense but that need that takes work diligence
but that need that takes work diligence
recollection reflection
maintenance of the context and enduring
of the pressure of acting out that you
don't don't give in to yes and and the
suit of girls you see the danger in
their sensuality you cultivate that
insight and the further away you you obviously
and the further away you you obviously
seeing something as dangerous you're
going to be moving away from them not
engaging and that results in the first
genre yeah the piece of pronunciation
that's you know so he's done nothing
else except reflect where debates are
where the traps are and we're drawing
himself from the traps there is no I
don't know what do I say what should I
say no to yeah because you haven't
reflected on things long enough if you
do it will become clearer and there'll
be layers and layers that you can peel
until you specifically directly
recognize the roots of central desire in
the beginning yeah you maybe have to say
no to too many things unnecessarily so
so it will cause you a bit more pain but
if you make the effort to reflect
recollect cultivate those insights it
will crystallize more and more and then
you really know I can relax actually
this is not dangerous that's not
dangerous there's no root in sensuality
but measure for that is the internal
knowledge not the external criteria or
the world of another
now obviously they said obvious things
that are always rooted in sensuality so
things basically
against the precepts and I mean like say
five precepts with the third person
being celibacy
that kind of an intoxication lying
stealing and all of that and Central
these are distraction
through your senses and sense objects
yeah so you need to say no to that
always you know like you can't go wrong
there because more often than not your
because more often than not your
intention will always be the rooting
sensuality when it comes to those things
but the cultivation needs to happen
often frequently reflecting
but just just saying no to things
well that's the thing people you you
start by saying no to things and what do
you do then do you just hope now there's
an account of you saying no truth will
become apparent or have you once you
said no are you now reflecting and
recollecting and cultivating insights
into danger Peril so that you don't have
to forcefully say no you simply wouldn't
want to go there when you recognize the
danger of it
it's funny because maybe some people say
you know the the pleasure of Jana will
will help you not go back to Century no
no that's the common misconception of
sensuality will will not make you go
back and that's the journey which is
what the pleasure of it is yeah which is
where the pleasure of John is yeah
I feel like this pleasure will surmount
this joy and satisfaction like yeah I'll get
joy and satisfaction like yeah I'll get
the pleasure so great that I will not
want any pleasure lesser than that well
that's like that's the definition of
sensuality that's exactly like let me
just get this and I'll never want
anything else again
that's like every Central desire doesn't
matter how big or small it might be
and even in that same suit it says uh
he was thinking about second John and he
understood why doesn't his his mind
launched out to get there you know the
same thing it's because he was finding
the light in that first time that
they're thinking in London and once he
saw that as an Affliction the danger in
that the danger the obstacle the lack of
refinement then yeah and when he
withdrew himself from first John into
second yeah so first genre is the
withdrawal from sensuality second gen is
withdrawal from the first Jana third
John is withdrawal from the second genre
four John is withdrawal from the third
genre it's not like oh I'll leap into it
and then this no no but completely
withdrawing abandoning design for this
removing any any kind of affinity
towards it seeing the danger the
parallel the the lack of satisfaction
that's how you enter the next one
by seeing the Affliction of the first
genre and there's that sort of the car
was it the similar in the car where
he steps on one stone yeah and doesn't
gain its balance and steadin is there
but it wants to step on the next one and
then Falls between the two so same like
somebody starts withdrawing from
centrality sensor forgiana but then he
wants a second genre and then he gets
neither
so withdrawal from desires internally
externally drying up